Irish literary miscellany collection, circa 1943-1998
Emory University
Irish literary miscellany collection, circa 1943-1998
Manuscript Collection No. 794
.5 linear ft. (1 box)
Collection composed of materials relating to Irish literature including correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, theatre programs, and Belfast Group worksheets.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, various sources.
Restrictions on access
Unrestricted access.
Scope and Content Note
The Irish literary miscellany collection is composed of individual items or small groups of items from various sources that do not relate directly to any of the division's other Irish literary collections. Materials include correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, theatre programs, and Belfast Group worksheets.
Arrangement Note
Arranged by record type.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Deane, Seamus, 1940-; Hewitt, John Harold, 1907-; Kilroy, Thomas.; Montague, John.
Corporate Names
Dolmen Press.; Belfast Group.
Topical Terms
English poetry--Irish authors--20th century.; Poets, Irish--20th century.; Theater--Ireland--20th century.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Theater programs.
Container list
- Belfast Group
- Belfast Group: Correspondence from Michael Allen regarding organizing, October 4, 1968 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Belfast Group Worksheet: Norman Dugdale Two in Connemara, Galatea to Pygmalion, Poor Fitz, Easter in Craven, Lines for an Old Lady, Against Abstraction, Sea-Change (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Belfast Group Worksheet: Norman Dugdale Seated King and Queen Dalesmen in Craven Anarchist A Study in Sepia Bog Nekuia (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Belfast Group Worksheet: Bernard MacLaverty St. Paul Could Hit the Nail on the Head (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Belfast Group Worksheet: Iris Bull Facets of War The Gulf A Backward Glance Without You A Walk in Winter Gifts Cavaliers Life's Little Ironies (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Opening Statement of Sebastian Barry at Emory University colloquium, November 11, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence
- Maeve Binchy postcards, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Peter Kavanagh to Joseph Gold, 1960, also includes newspaper clippings concerning the publication of The John Quinn Letters: A Pandect (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Dolmen Press
- "Books Published in Limited Editions at the Dolmen Press," June 1962, prospectus (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Manuscripts
- Deane, Seamus "The Churchyard in Cregan" [translation of Úirchill au Chreagáin], 3 MS drafts. [accession 97-07-03] (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hewitt, John "Freehold" [including "Feathers on Turf," "The Lonely Heart," "Townland of Peace," "The Glittering Sod," and "Roll Call"], offprint [from Lagan?] w/ several corrections in Hewitt’s hand. [accession 96-12-02] (Box 1, Folder 11)
- McDonagh, Martin The Skull in Connemara, [early title for the Lonesome West], signed TS with corrections. [accession 2003-05-02] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Montague, John, "The Trout," MS with note regarding revision of the poem. Originally laid in Special Collections' copy of A Chosen Light (PR6063 .055 C45). (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photographs
- Berkeley, Sara [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Carson, Ciaran [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Clarke, Austin [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Cronin, Anthony, photographed by John Minihan, 1989 [accession 2002-03-13] (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Davitt, Michael, photographed by Lesley Doyle [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Deane, Seamus, photographed by Caroline Forbes [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Dhomhnaill, Nuala Ni, photographed by John Minihan, Prague, 1997 [accession 2002-03-13] (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Ennis, John [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Fiacc, Padraic [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Hewitt, John [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Kennelly, Brendan, photographed by Eimear O’Connor (2) [accession 97-11-04] and John Minihan, 1997 [accession 2002-03-13] (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Lewis, Cecil Day, photographed by Paul Levitton [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Longley, Michael, photographed by John Minihan, Dublin, 1991 [accession 2002-03-13] (Box 1, Folder 26)
- McNeice, Louis, photographed by Gallery Press [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Montague, John, photographed by Gallery Press [accession 97-11-04] and John Minihan, 1997 [accession 2002-03-13] (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Murphy, Richard, photographed by Albert Fenton and Stephen Moreton-Pritchard [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 29)
- O’Grady, Desmond, photographed by Peggy Mulholland, 1995 [accession 97-11-04] and John Minihan, 1989 [accession 2002-03-13] (Box 1, Folder 30)
- O Riordain, Sean, photographed by James, G. Maguire [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Ó Searcaigh, Cathal, photographed by Rachel Brown [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Simmons, James, photographed by Germaine Lot [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Stewart, Francis and his wife Finola Graham, photographed by John Minihan, 1989 [accession 2002-03-13] (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Stoppard, Tom [gift of Richard Ellmann, 1983] (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Sweeney, Matthew, photographed by John Minihan [accession 97-11-04] (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Thomas, Dylan, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Trevor, William, photographed by John Minihan, 1982 (2) [accession 2002-03-13] (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Trinity College, Dublin, photographed by John Minihan, 1998 [accession 2002-03-13] (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Theatre Programs: Capitol Theatre (discontinued)
- Hofmannsthal, Hugo von, Everyman: 5 April 1953 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Theatre Programs: Dublin University Art Society
- Beckettcetera: 8-12 February [post 1965] (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Theatre Programs: Field Day Theatre
- Kilroy, Thomas, The Madame MacAdam, theatre program from Field Day Theatre Company production, [1991] (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Theatre Programs: Gaiety Theatre
- Podrecca’s Piccoli Theatre, Marionette Revue: 17 April 1954 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Synge, John Millington, The Playboy of the Western World: 5 July 1954 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- O’Casey, Sean, The Bishop's Bonfire: 28 February 1955 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Shaw, George Bernard, Androcles and the Lion; Lady Gregory, The Rising of the Moon: 2 July 1956 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Feydeau, Georges (translated by Peter Meyer), Sauce for the Goose: 3 October 1978 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- O’Casey, Sean, Juno and the Paycock: 21 April 1994 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Theatre Programs: Gate Theatre
- Edwards, Hilton, "Jack-in-the-Box" and the Future: 16th Jan. 1943. [Attended, as per autograph inscription on verso, by "Mother [Mrs Richard James Hoskin (nee Barbara Hetherington)], Mrs [Phoebie] Cameron, Mrs [Florence] Holmes [nee Cameron], Phoebie [Holmes, now Bennett], Barbara [Robinson, now Wright] and myself (Rosaleen Hilda Robinson, nee Hoskin] (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Anouilh, Jean (translated by Christopher FRY), Ring Round the Moon: 195? (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Sophochles (a version by W.B. Yeats), Oedipus, the King; Shaw, Bernard, The Man of Destiny: 195? (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Shaw, Bernard, Saint Joan: 195? (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Eliot, T. S., The Cocktail Party: August 1953 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Eliot, T.S., The Family Reunion: July 1954 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Mac Liammoir, Micheal, A Slipper for the Moon: December 1954 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Pirandello, Luigi, The Masquerade of Henry IV: April 1955 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Greene, Graham, The Living Room: May-June 1955 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Shaffer, Peter, Amadeus: 17 February 1982 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Coward, Noel, Blithe Spirit: 4 December 1985 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Shakespeare, William, Twelfth Night: 6 December 1988 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Chekhov, Anton (in a version by Frank McGuinness), Three Sisters: 28 March 1990 [with associated Irish Times article or 7 May 1990 and published details of Michael Pennington's one-man show, Anton Chekhov] (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Brecht, Bertolt and Kurt Weil (in a version by Frank McGuinness), The Threepenny Opera, 9 July 1991; Beckett, Samuel, Waiting for Godot: 7 February 1992 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Ibsen, Henrik, A Doll's House: 5 October 1993 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Austen, Jane (adapted by James Maxwell), Pride and Prejudice: 1 December 1994 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Theatre Programs: Irish Theatre Company
- Wilder, Thornton, Our Town; Ibsen, Henrik, An Enemy of the People: Spring Tour 1980 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Theatre Programs: Olympia Theatre
- Ibsen, Henrik (adapted by Max Faber), Hedda Gabler: 5 July 1954 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Rattigan, Terence, The Deep Blue Sea: 27 September 1954 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Davies, Rhys, No Escape: 11 October 1954 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Carroll, Paul Vincent, The Devil Came from Dublin!: 2 May 1955 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Shakespeare, William, Macbeth: 27 June 1955 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Giraudoux, Jean, The Madwoman of Chaillot: 25 July 1955 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Azuma Kabuki: 31 October 1955 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Balzac, Honore de, Le Faiseur: 20 May 1957 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Joyce Grenfell " At Home": 16 September 1957 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Danish Patomimeteater, Harlequin's Mechanical Statue: 2 December 1957 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Stoppard, Tom and Andre Previn, Every Good Boy Deserves Favour: 1 October 1979 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Theatre Programs: Peacock Theatre
- Patrick Gulliver, based on the work of Jonathan Swift: 20 June 1978 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Joycemen; based on James Joyce’s Ulysses: 10 November 1980 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Beckett, Samuel, Happy Days: 22 May 1986 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Mac Intyre Tom, Snow White: 27 June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Theatre Programs: Pike Theatre
- More Follies of Herbert Lane: 195?. Programme noteworthy for drawing by Pauline Bewick and for being designed and printed at the Dolmen Press [note by Barbara Wright]. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Theatre Programs: Royal Irish Academy of Music
- Yeats, W.B., The Countess Cathleen: 29-30 April 1954 [Organised as part of "An Tostal." an ephemeral Arts Festival, which took place in Dublin in 1954; harp accompaniments by Barbara Robinson now Wright (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Theatre Programs: Saint Patrick’s Cathedral
- Eliot, T.S., Murder in the Cathedral: September/October 1962 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Posters
- "Broadsheet 1967-1978: Poetry Prose and Graphics," National Library of Scotland, 5 February-20 April 1983 (Box OP1)